Norman Frederick papers, Inclusive: 1951-1965, undated, Bulk: 1950-1960, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Norman Frederick papers
Inclusive: 1951-1965, undated, Bulk: 1950-1960, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
560
Norman, Frederick
10 folders.
The Norman Frederick papers contain photographs of the Waco area, the Waco Y.M.C.A., and newspaper clippings concerning Norman Frederick.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Norman Frederick was born on 1916 June 24 in Pennsylvania. He attended Springfield College in Springfield, Massachusetts, and then served for 4.5 years in the Navy. He married Hayle Wellbaum Frederick in 1944. Frederick became the physical director of the Waco Youth Men's Christian Association (Y.M.C.A.) and served in that position for 10 years, developing his passion for physical education. In 1960 Frederick accepted a position at Baylor, where he taught courses in wrestling, swimming, and volleyball. While at Baylor, Frederick became interested in increasing participation in the university's intramural program. He became the Intramural Director in 1962 and was promoted to Coordinator of Men's and Women's Intramural Sports Programs in 1963. Frederick also participated as Secretary in the Heart of Texas Ramblers organization. Frederick died on 1995 July 1 in McLennan County and is buried in the Greenwood Memorial Park and Mausoleum in Fort Worth, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Norman Frederick papers consist of materials from the mid-twentieth century, with some undated items particularly concerning the Waco Y.M.C.A.
Series I, Press, contains newspaper clippings. Series II, Photographic Material, contains photographs, filed topically and then chronologically. Series III, Collected Materials, contains a greeting card and handwritten notes.
Arrangement
The collection came in two envelopes. There was no discernible arrangement.
The collection is currently arranged into three series: I. Press, II. Photographic Materials, and III. Collected Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 560. Acquired 2019-08-29
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. "Norman H. Frederick." Memorial #55077195. Databases. Accessed 2019 September 23.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Faculty -- Photographs.
Subjects
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); College Sports -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; Men -- Texas -- Waco -- Societies and clubs.; Photographs.; Physical education and training.; Young Men's Christian associations -- Texas.
- Press, 1961-1965, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains newspaper clippings. The series is in average condition.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1961-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographic Materials, 1951-1959, undated; 2
  This series contains photographs. The series is in average condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Y.M.C.A. Cookout, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Y.M.C.A. Basketball Photographs, 1951-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Y.M.C.A. Swimming Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Y.M.C.A. Baseball, Softball, Table Tennis, and Weight Room Photographs, 1954-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Y.M.C.A. Massage/Spa Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Y.M.C.A. Buildings and Aerial Waco Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Meetings and Dinners Photographs, 1952-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Floyd Casey Photographs, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Collected Materials, undated; 3
  This series contains a greeting card and notes. The series is in average condition.
  - Greeting Cards and Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)